A Guide to the Governor Robert F. McDonnell, Policy Office, Records, 1997; 2007-2014 (bulk 2010-2013)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor Robert F. McDonnell, Policy Office, Records, 1997; 2007-2014 (bulk 2010-2013)
The Library of Virginia
51142 and 52781
65.4 cu. ft. (109 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219, accession 51142 transferred on 9 January 2014; accession 52781 transferred on 24 July 2019.
Historical Information
The Policy Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. During Governor Robert McDonnell's administration, the Policy Office was responsible for identifying emerging issues, implementing gubernatorial initiatives, and providing policy and political advice to the Governor. The Policy Office worked with the Cabinet and Administration to develop gubernatorial policies and conduct outreach to key stake holders. The Policy Office was responsible for managing the legislative process (preparing bills and legislative packages and reviewing bills), reviewing budget requests, and ensuring agency performance in implementing the administration's agenda.
Governor McDonnell established the policy framework for his administration on his first full day in office through two executive orders. On 16 January 2010, Governor McDonnell issued Executive Order One establishing the Chief Job Creation Officer and the Governor's Economic Development and Job Creation Commission. McDonnell named Lieutenant Governor Bill Bolling as Chief Jobs Officer who served as co-chair of the Commission. Other Commission members included the Secretaries of Commerce and Trade, Agriculture and Forestry, Natural Resources, Transportation, Technology, Finance, Education and Administration, or their designees. The Commission also included citizens representing a cross segment of industry and business sectors, including small and rural businesses. Governor McDonnell charged the Commission with: identifying impediments to and opportunities for job creation; review how other states and foreign countries attracted jobs and how Virginia could replicate and improve upon those initiatives; review the agencies' role in job creation and make recommendations on those efforts could be better coordinated; make recommendations on new investments and changes to the tax and regulatory environment of Virginia; evaluate current programs and investments designed to develop the workforce and attract and retain businesses in Virginia; and assist the Virginia Economic Development Partnership to identify and target industries and businesses to recruit to Virginia.
The Commission created focusing on six key economic development priorities: business recruitment and retention; economically challenged regions and localities; energy research, exploration and production; small business; tourism and film marketing; and real estate and construction.
The archived website of the Governor's Commission on Economic Development and Job Creation includes meeting materials, presentations, reports and news releases.
On 16 January 2010, Governor McDonnell issued Executive Order Two establishing the Governor's Commission on Government Reform and Restructuring. The Commission was charged with conducting a thorough review of Virginia state government. Specifically, they focused on four areas: identifying opportunities for creating efficiencies in state government, including streamlining, consolidating, or eliminating redundant and unnecessary agency services, governing bodies, regulations and programs; explore innovative ways to deliver state services at the lowest cost and best value to Virginia taxpayers; seek out means to more effectively and efficiently perform core state functions, including privatization of government operations where appropriate; and examine ways for state government to be more transparent, user friendly and accountable. Executive Order 32, issued 12 April 2011, continued the work of the Commission.
The archived website of the Governor's Commission on Government Reform and Restructuring includes meeting materials, presentations, reports and news releases.
Other major policy initiatives focused on education, health care, higher education and transportation. Some of the education initiatives included the establishment of an A-F grading system for all Virginia schools, increased the number of K-12 STEM academies, virtual schools and the administration's Opportunity to Learn Education Reform legislation. The Virginia Health Reform Initiative Advisory Council provided recommendations a comprehensive strategy for implementing health reform to increase efficiency delivery of high quality health care at a lower cost. The administration also successfully negotiated a major settlement agreement to resolve a complaint by the United States Department of Justice regarding individuals residing at a training center. The Governor's Higher Education Commission, created by Executive Order Nine on 26 March 2010, was charged with developing "a comprehensive strategy for increased educational attainment, skills development, and lifelong learning." It recommended legislation, "Preparing for the Top Jobs of the 21st Century: The Virginia Higher Education Opportunity Act of 2011," focusing on economic opportunity, reform-based investment and affordable access. The Virginia General Assembly passed legislation enacting many of the Commissions recommendations in 2011. In 2013, Virginia passed the administration's long-term transportation funding plan.
Scope and Content
The Governor Robert F. McDonnell, Policy Office, Records are housed in 109 boxes. The collection is arranged into four (4) series. Series have been designated for: I. Legislative Guidance and Review; II. Regulations; III. Judicial Appointments; and IV. Subject Files. These records include agreements, reports, correspondence, e-mail, memorandums, legal files, legislation, regulations, budget documents, agendas, handouts, talking points and meeting notes. These records document the work of the Policy Office during the McDonnell administration and were created or collected, 2010-2014, though some documents in this collection pre-date this time period.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Legislative Guidance and Review, 2009-2013
II. Regulations, 2009-2013
III. Judicial Appointments, 2010-2013
IV. Subject Files, 1997, 2007-2014 (bulk 2010-2013)
Related Material
OFFICE OF THE GOVERNOR-ROBERT F. MCDONNELL
The Governor Robert F. McDonnell Administration Web Archive Collection, 2010-2014. This collection preserves the web sites that document the 2010-2014 administration of Virginia's 71st governor, Bob McDonnell. Included in the collection are the web sites for the governor, his cabinet secretaries and issues and initiatives. Also included are the web sites of the First Lady (Maureen McDonnell), Lt. Governor (Bill Bolling), and Attorney General (Ken Cuccinelli).
The Correspondence and Supporting Documentation of the Executive Office of Governor Robert F. McDonnell, 2010-2013 (bulk 2010-2011) Collection
The Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell's Governor Robert F. McDonnell, Executive Office-Deputy Chief of Staff Matt Conrad, Records, 2011-2013 Collection
The Records of Governor Robert F. McDonnell, Executive Office-Counselor's Office, 2002-2003; 2006-2013 (bulk 2010-2013) Collection
The Records of the Executive Mansion of Governor Robert F. McDonnell, 2010-2014 Collection
CABINET OF GOVERNOR ROBERT F. MCDONNELL
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Administration, 2010-2013 Collection
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2005-2013 (bulk 2010-2013) Collection
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 1998-2014 (bulk 2010-2013) Collection
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Education, 2006-2014 (bulk 2009-2013) Collection
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Finance, 2007-2013 Collection
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 2010-2013 Collection
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources, 2002-2014 (bulk 2009-2013) Collection
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety and Homeland Security, 2006-2013 (bulk 2010-2013) Collection
The Records of the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety, 2010-2013 (bulk 2012-2013) Collection
The Records of the Secretary of Transportation, 2009-2013 Collection
The Records of the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security, 2005-2012 (bulk 2010-2011) Collection
SECRETARY OF THE COMMONWEALTH FOR GOVERNOR ROBERT F. MCDONNELL
The Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 2010-2014 Collection
The Constituent Correspondence of Governor Robert F. McDonnell, 2009-2013 (bulk 2010-2013) Collection
The Constituent Correspondence of Governor Robert F. McDonnell, Mass Mailings, 2009-2013 (bulk 2010-2013) Collection
The Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Governor's Fellows Program, 2010-2011 Collection
The Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Oaths, 1998-2013 Collection
The Records of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Working Files and Tracking Documents, 2010-2014 (bulk 2011-2013) Collection
LIVE WEBSITES
The Virginia General Assembly's Legislative Information System contains searchable databases for bills and resolutions from 1994 to the present and reports to the general assembly. It also includes links to the Code of Virginia, Virginia Administrative Code, Constitution of Virginia, Charters, Authorities, Compacts and Uncodified Acts.
The Virginia Regulatory Town Hall website provides information about proposed changes to Virginia's regulations, including a meetings calendar and board minutes.
The Virginia State Budget Portal provides information about Budget Bills, Budget Amendments, and Committee Reports related to the budget from 1996 to the present.
The Virginia Department of Planning and Budget assists the Governor's Office, General Assembly, and state agencies develop and implement the budget. The website contains information on Virginia's budget from 2000 to the present.
Contents List
- I. Legislative Guidance and Review, 2009-2013., Extent: 37.8 cubic feet (43 boxes). (Box 1-43)
  The Legislative Guidance and Review series is housed in 43 boxes and is arranged into two (2) subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Legislative Files and B. Legislative Guidance. These files include correspondence, legislative files, budget documents, along with subject files and supporting materials such as briefs, meeting records, presentations, and reports. This series documents the Governor's Policy Office guidance to, as well as the review by, Planning and Budget, Cabinet officials, Executive staff and agency heads in regards to legislative and budget matters.
  - Subseries I.A. Legislative Files, 2010-2013., Extent: 35 cubic feet (35 boxes) (Box 1-34; 43)
    This subseries is housed in 35 boxes. The original file order has been maintained. Each legislative file usually contains: the text of each bill including any amendments, bill tracking information, Governor's Summaries (prepared by the Division of Legislative Services), Legislative Action Summaries (for bills tabled, withdrawn or killed in committee), Governor's Policy Office Enrolled Bill Review Forms, Enrolled Bill Reviews (by Cabinet Secretary), Department of Planning and Budget Fiscal Impact Statements, and the Attorney General's Recommendations to the Governor (restricted for 75 years - attorney/client privilege).
    - 2010 Session
      - House of Delegates (Legislative Action Summaries)
        - HB 1-312 (Box 1)
        - HB 313-613 (Box 2)
        - HB 617-1072 (Box 3)
        - HB 1077-1384 (Box 4)
      - Senate (Legislative Action Summaries)
        - SB 1-300 (Box 5)
        - SB 301-733 (Box 6)
      - House of Delegates (Enrolled Bill Review)
        - HB 1-377 (Box 7)
        - HB 382-714 (Box 8)
        - HB 715-1039 (Box 9)
        - HB 1040-1396 (Box 10)
      - Senate (Enrolled Bill Review)
        - SB 1-220 (Box 11)
        - SB 232-461 (Box 12)
        - SB 465-739 (Box 13)
    - 2011 Session
      - Proposed Agency Legislation
        - Secretary of Administration-Secretary of Technology, 2010. (Box 14)
        - Secretary of Transportation, 2010. (Box 15)
      - House of Delegates
        - HB 1399-1772 (Box 16)
        - HB 1773-2093 (Box 17)
        - HB 2094-2553 (Box 18)
      - Senate
        - SB 742-987 (Box 19)
        - SB 988-1214 (Box 20)
        - SB 1215-1486 (Box 21)
    - 2012 Session
      - House of Delegates
        - HB 3-299 (Box 22)
        - HB 300-599 (Box 23)
        - HB 601-897 (Box 24)
        - HB 900-1095 (Box 25)
        - HB 1102-1298 (Box 26)
      - Senate
        - SB 1-369 (Box 27)
        - SB 370-686; Veto Session (Box 28)
    - 2013 Session
      - House of Delegates
        - HB 1305-1699 (Box 29)
        - HB 1701-2045 (Box 30)
        - HB 2052-2344 (Box 43)
      - Senate
        - SB 688-1027 (Box 31)
        - SB 1028-1198 (Box 32)
        - SB 1200-1376 (Box 33)
      - Veto Session and Amendments
        - HB 1350-2347; SB 744-1378 (Box 34)
  - Subseries I.B. Legislative Guidance, 2009-2013., Extent: 2.8 cubic feet (8 boxes) (Box 35-42)
    This subseries is housed in eight (8) boxes and is arranged roughly chronological order. The legislative guidance records include proposed legislation from cabinet secretariats, governor's bills, and research for legislation related to governor's initiatives such as government reform, ABC privatization, transportation funding, and tax reform.
    - 2010 Session
      - 2010 Proposed Legislation - Public Safety, 9 December 2009. (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - Executive Biennial Budget, 2010-2012, Finance, 18 December 2009. (Box 35, Folder 2)
      - Administration, Governor and Agency Bills, 19 January 2010. (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - Commerce and Trade, Governor and Agency Bills, 19 January 2010. (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - Finance, Governor and Agency Bills, 19 January 2010. (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - Health and Human Resources, Governor and Agency Bills, 19 January 2010. (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - Transportation, Governor and Agency Bills, 19 January 2010. (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - Supporting Documents for the Introduced Budgets (1 of 2), January 2010. (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - Supporting Documents for the Introduced Budgets (2 of 2), January 2010. (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - Governor's Legislation 2010 (1 of 2), 9 February 2010. (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - Governor's Legislation 2010 (2 of 2), 9 February 2010. (Box 36, Folder 2)
      - Amendments 30 Day Bills, April 2010. (Box 36, Folder 3)
      - Talking Points 30 Day Recommendations, April 2010. (Box 36, Folder 4)
      - Budget Amendments and Talking Points 2010, 15 April 2010. (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Reports
      - A Disparity Study for the Commonwealth of Virginia, MGT of American, Inc., 13 January 2010. (Box 36, Folder 6)
      - FY 2010 Agency SWaM Procurement Plan and Summary, 2010. (Box 37, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Dept. of Taxation, Consolidating the Administration of Certain Taxes, 27 August 2010. (Box 37, Folder 2)
      - Operational Review Task Force Final Reports, 18 November 2010. (Box 37, Folder 3)
      - ABC Privatization, Part 1, 2010. (Box 37, Folder 4)
      - ABC Privatization, Part 1, 2010. (Box 37, Folder 5)
      - ABC Privatization, Part 1, 2010. (Box 37, Folder 6)
      - ABC Privatization, Part 2, 2010. (Box 38, Folder 1)
      - ABC Privatization, Part 2, 2010. (Box 38, Folder 2)
      - ABC Privatization, Part 2, 2010. (Box 38, Folder 3)
      - ABC Privatization, Miscellaneous Documents, 2010. (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - 2011 Session
      - 2011 Agency Bill Fact Sheets (1 of 2), 15 December 2010. (Box 38, Folder 5)
      - 2011 Agency Bill Fact Sheets (2 of 2), 15 December 2010. (Box 38, Folder 6)
      - 2011 Session (Overview), 2011. (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - HB 2259 (2011) Uniform Computer Information Transactions Act, 2011. (Box 39, Folder 2)
      - Government Reform Bills, 2011. (Box 39, Folder 3)
      - Government Reform, Governor's Bills Talking Points, 2011. (Box 39, Folder 4)
      - Governor McDonnell's 2011 Budget Amendments, 2011. (Box 39, Folder 5)
      - Governor McDonnell's 2011 Legislative Package for Transportation Funding and Reform, 2010-2011. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Reports
      - Cutting the Red Tape in Virginia: Streamlining Unnecessary Government Regulations to Promote Economic Welfare by 2011 Governor's Fellows, July 2011. (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Virginia's Drug Treatment Courts: Expanding a Proven Solution throughout the Commonwealth, 2011 Governor's Fellows Research Project, July 2011. (Box 39, Folder 2)
      - Coal and Energy Commission, Proposals, Studies and Presentations on Uranium Mining in Virginia, November 2011. (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - 2012 Session
      - 2012 General Assembly Session, HHR Agency Legislation Proposals (1 of 4), 22 August 2011. (Box 40, Folder 1)
      - 2012 General Assembly Session, HHR Agency Legislation Proposals (2 of 4), 22 August 2011. (Box 40, Folder 2)
      - 2012 General Assembly Session, HHR Agency Legislation Proposals (3 of 4), 22 August 2011. (Box 40, Folder 3)
      - 2012 General Assembly Session, HHR Agency Legislation Proposals (4 of 4), 22 August 2011. (Box 40, Folder 4)
      - Government Reform Agency Feedback, Fall 2011. (Box 40, Folder 5)
      - 2012 Tax Reform Options, 2 October 2011. (Box 40, Folder 6)
      - 2012 General Assembly Legislative Working Group, Transportation (1 of 3), Fall 2011. (Box 40, Folder 7)
      - 2012 General Assembly Legislative Working Group, Transportation (2 of 3), Fall 2011. (Box 41, Folder 1)
      - 2012 General Assembly Legislative Working Group, Transportation (3 of 3), Fall 2011. (Box 41, Folder 2)
      - Governor's Bills Talking Points, January 2012. (Box 41, Folder 3)
      - The Opportunity to Learn K-12 Education Agenda, Phase 2, 2012 General Assembly, January 2012. (Box 41, Folder 4)
      - The Case for Reform: A Product of the Governor's Commission on Government Reform and Restructuring, January 2012. (Box 41, Folder 5)
      - House Commerce and Labor Committee, Governor's Bills Key Points and Agency Bills Key Points, 2012 Session, 2012. (Box 41, Folder 6)
      - Talking Points: Governor and Agency Bills, 2012 Session (1 of 2), 2012. (Box 41, Folder 7)
      - Talking Points: Governor and Agency Bills, 2012 Session (2 of 2), 2012. (Box 41, Folder 8)
      - Reconvene Session 2012, Governor's Amendment and Veto Key Points, Jasen Eige, 2012. (Box 41, Folder 9)
      - Budget Documents, J. Jasen Eige (1 of 2), September-November 2011. (Box 42, Folder 1)
      - Budget Documents, J. Jasen Eige (2 of 2), September-November 2011. (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Reports
      - Policy Venture to Research Triangle Park, 20 June 2012. (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - 2013 Session
      - Virginia Dept. of Taxation, Tax Reform Alternatives, November 2012. (Box 42, Folder 4)
      - Governor's Amendments Talking Points, House Version, April 2013. (Box 42, Folder 5)
- II. Regulations, 2009-2013., Extent: 7 cubic feet (7 boxes). (Box 44-50)
  The Regulations series is housed in 7 boxes and is arranged roughly in chronological order. This series was processed using minimal processing standards: the records have not been refoldered and the original order maintained. The series consists of regulation review forms, memorandums, recommendations, and summary of regulations.
  This series documents the McDonnell Administration's executive branch review of Virginia's Regulatory Process. Before a regulation become available for public comment on Town Hall, Virginia's regulatory website, it often undergoes review by the Department of Planning and Budget, the responsible Cabinet Secretary and the Governor (via the Policy Office). The Office of the Attorney General also may review the regulation. Each regulation reviewed by the Policy Office usually includes a Regulatory Review Form, memorandum(s) from the Department of Planning and Budget (DPB) and the Town Hall posting. Most of the information in these records is available on the most of file is available on the Virginia Regulatory Town Hall website: https://townhall.virginia.gov/. There are two documents in the files that do not appear online: Governor's Policy Office Regulation Review Form and DPB Regulation Review Memorandum.
  - 2009-2012 (bulk 2010) (Box 44)
  - 2009-2012 (bulk 2010) (Box 45)
  - 2010-2012 (bulk 2011) (Box 46)
  - 2009-2012 (bulk 2010-2011) (Box 47)
  - 2010-2013 (bulk 2012-2013) (Box 48)
  - 2011-2013 (bulk 2012-2013) (Box 49)
  - 2013 (Box 50)
- III. Judicial Appointments, 2010-2013., Extent: 2.1 cubic feet (6 boxes). (Box 51-56)
  The Judicial Appointments series is housed in six (6) boxes and is arranged into four (4) subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Supreme Court of Virginia; B. Virginia Court of Appeals; C. Circuit Court; and D. District Court. Judges of the Circuit Court, Court of Appeals, Supreme Court of Virginia are elected by a majority of each house of the General Assembly (8 year terms for Circuit Court and Court of Appeals; 12 year term for the Supreme Court of Virginia). Interim appointments are made by the Governor subject to election by the General Assembly at the next regular session. Records for each applicant usually include: letter of interest, letters of support, resume, Virginia State Bar Judicial Questionnaire, and Statement of Economic Interest. The applications are considered personnel files and are closed for 75 years per Code of Virginia, 42.1-78.
  - Selection Process (Open)
    - Selection Process, 2011. (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Selection Process, 2011. (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - General Information, 2011. (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Subseries III.A. Supreme Court of Virginia,, 2010-2011 (bulk 2011)., Extent: 0.7 cubic feet (2 boxes) (Box 51-52)
    The applications are considered personnel files and are closed for 75 years per Code of Virginia, 42.1-78.
    - General Information, 2010-2011. (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Baskervill, Pamela S., 2011. (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Beales, Randolph Allen, 2011. (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Emmert, L. Steven, 2011. (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Huff, Glen A., 2011. (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Humphreys, Robert J., 2011. (Box 51, Folder 9)
    - Irvine, Michael S., 2011. (Box 51, Folder 10)
    - Kelsey, D. Arthur, 2010-2011. (Box 51, Folder 11)
    - Knicely, James J., 2011. (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - Ludwig, Victor V., 2011. (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Martin, George, undated. (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - McClanahan, Elizabeth Ann, 2011. (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - McCullough, Stephen R., 2011. (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Milam, Joseph W., 2011. (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Monday, Monica Taylor, 2011. (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Padrick, H. Thomas, 2011. (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Powell, Cleo E., 2011. (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Theo, William E., 2011. (Box 52, Folder 9)
  - Subseries III.B. Virginia Court of Appeals, 2011; 2013., Extent: 0.35 cubic feet (1 box) (Box 53)
    - Earley, Sr., Mark L., 2011. (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Mullins, Stanford T., 2011. (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - Showalter, Josiah T., 2011. (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Court of Appeals Vacancy, 2013. (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - Decker, Marla G., 2013. (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - Lief, Joshua N., 2013. (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - Martin, James C., 2013. (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - McCahill, Burke F., 2013. (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - Milam, Jr., Joseph W., 2013. (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - Nagel, Patricia P., 2013. (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - Sanders, Jr., Elwood (1 of 2), 2013. (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - Sanders, Jr., Elwood (2 of 2), 2013. (Box 53, Folder 12)